<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The 30 Anthropik Theses</title>
    <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/</link>
    <description>Recent content on The 30 Anthropik Theses</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2005 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://rewild.com/anthropik/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #5: Humans are neither good nor evil</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/humans-are-neither-good-nor-evil/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2005 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/humans-are-neither-good-nor-evil/</guid>
      <description>Are humans essentially good, or essentially evil? This is one of the most basic, perennial questions in philosophy. Many identify our individual answers to this question as determing our political spectrum–conservatives believe humans are inherently evil, and require strict rules to make them good, while liberals believe humans are inherently good, and must simply be free to act on such goodness. Both positions are unrealistic. Humans are products of evolution, and evolution is unconcerned with such abstractions as “good” or “evil.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #4: Human population is a function of food supply</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/human-population-is-a-function-of-food-supply/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2005 01:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/human-population-is-a-function-of-food-supply/</guid>
      <description>Thomas Malthus was one of the most influential thinkers of all time. His father knew Hume and Rousseau, and his own paper–*An Essay on the Principle of Population*–forever changed the way we think about populations and food supplies. It has informed food security policies worldwide, and provided the basic underpinnings of our modern concern with overpopulation. In The Origin of Species, Darwin called his theory of natural selection an application of the doctrines of Malthus in an area without the complicating factor of human intelligence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #3: Humans are products of evolution</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/humans-are-the-product-of-evolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2005 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/humans-are-the-product-of-evolution/</guid>
      <description>As we saw in the second thesis, natural selection is a tautology: anything that possesses some trait that makes it more likely to propogate itself, is more likely to propogate itself. Played out over a sufficiently long timeline, this can easily explain the origin of species. It was an explosive idea; not because it was theoretically lacking, nor even for lack of evidence. It was not even explosive for what it ruled out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #2: Evolution is the result of diversity</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/evolution-is-the-result-of-diversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2005 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/evolution-is-the-result-of-diversity/</guid>
      <description>The concept of progress is actually rather new. Most prehistoric and ancient peoples saw history as a constantly repeating cycle, incompatible with any notion of advancement or degradation. The first conceptions of linear time are found only in the historical era. Confuscius, the Greeks and the Jews all believed that the world was, in fact, becoming worse. In this, they did concieve of history as linear, but as the opposite of progress.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #1: Diversity is the primary good</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/diversity-is-the-primary-good/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2005 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/diversity-is-the-primary-good/</guid>
      <description>Humans are social animals, and also capable of abstract, independent thought. The combination requires some form of social standards. Bees think with a single hive mind, and solitary animals do not encounter one another often enough to require a rigid system of morality and ethics. Without social norms, however, human society would break down. We have evolved in such societies, and require other humans to live. A single human, on his own, has little chance of survival.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>