<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The 30 Anthropik Theses</title>
    <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/</link>
    <description>Recent content on The 30 Anthropik Theses</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2008 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://rewild.com/anthropik/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Noble or Savage? Both. (Part 1)</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/noble-or-savage-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2008 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/noble-or-savage-part-1/</guid>
      <description>I have already had a few commenters direct me to &amp;ldquo;Noble or Savage?,&amp;rdquo; the article from the Dec. 19 *Economist* magazine. The article has not raised my low opinion of this periodical. As Kenneth Boulding so correctly assessed, &amp;ldquo;Anyone who believes that growth can go on forever in a finite world is either a madman or an economist.&amp;rdquo; You may recall that *The Economist* teamed up with Shell some years back gave us the absurdist essay contest question, &amp;ldquo;Do we need nature?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #19: Complexity ensures collapse</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/complexity-ensures-collapse/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2005 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/complexity-ensures-collapse/</guid>
      <description>Predicting the proximate cause of collapse is impossible, though, as we have seen, both environmental problems and peak oil present serious threats&amp;ndash;precisely the kind of threat that has toppled civilizations in the past. On their own, however, such proximate causes are probabilistic. Peak oil may mean the end of civilization; or, perhaps we will be able to transition to some alternative. Environmental problems may destroy the most basic necessities of civilized life, or perhaps we will solve them, instead.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #18: Peak Oil may lead to collapse</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/peak-oil-may-lead-to-collapse/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2005 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/peak-oil-may-lead-to-collapse/</guid>
      <description>Energy, like matter, cannot be created&amp;ndash;it can only be transformed. That is the Law of Conservation of Mass-Energy, which also entails that matter can be transformed into energy, making matter and energy differing states of the same thing. When you burn wood, part of the wood&amp;rsquo;s matter is converted into energy&amp;ndash;the light and heat of fire. Fossil fuels are created out of organic matter, by applying eons of pressure deep inside the earth to the remains of dead plants and animals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #17: Environmental problems may lead to collapse</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/environmental-problems-may-lead-to-collapse/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2005 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/environmental-problems-may-lead-to-collapse/</guid>
      <description>In Collapse, Jared Diamond argues that civilizations *choose to collapse by neglecting their ecology. He spends most of his volume pointing to numerous examples of how civilizations collapsed because of ecological problems on Easter Island, Greenland, the southwest United States, and the Yucatan peninsula. He highlights the ecological role in conflicts in Rwanda, Haiti, Montana, China and Australia; he even provides a map which illustrates the nearly perfect overlap between the world&amp;rsquo;s most ecologically distressed areas, and its most politically distressed areas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #16: Technology cannot stop collapse</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/technology-cannot-stop-collapse/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2005 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/technology-cannot-stop-collapse/</guid>
      <description>Invariably, the threat of our own civilization&amp;rsquo;s collapse is readily answered with the hope of technological progress. Progressivists deny that we face any systemic problems, only technical problems, with technical solutions. As we have seen in the previous theses, this is most certainly not the case, but the question remains: could these systemic problems be solved through the proper application of technology? Technophiliacs and techno-utopians often wax poetic for the prospects of our technological future.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #15: We have passed the point of diminishing returns</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/we-have-passed-the-point-of-diminishing-returns/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2005 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/we-have-passed-the-point-of-diminishing-returns/</guid>
      <description>In the previous thesis, we saw that complexity is subject to diminishing returns, because of each of its facets&amp;ndash;subsistence, information processing, sociopolitical control, economics, and technology&amp;ndash;are not only intertwined as a single system, but are themselves subject to diminishing returns. As such, any society which pursues complexity as an answer to every stress&amp;ndash;which is to say, any civilization (see thesis #13)&amp;ndash;must, eventually, collapse. This is only underlined by the basic fact that nothing can grow forever in a finite universe (see thesis #12).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #14: Complexity is subject to diminishing returns</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/complexity-is-subject-to-diminishing-returns/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2005 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/complexity-is-subject-to-diminishing-returns/</guid>
      <description>Joseph Tainter&amp;rsquo;s 1988 *The Collapse of Complex Societies* remains the definitive work in the field of collapse. Tainter reviews other explanations of collapse&amp;ndash;including economics, invasion and environmental problems&amp;ndash;and finds them all insufficient. While these factors certainly play their roles, these are also the very same stressors that complexity is *supposed* to deal with. Thus, while these might suffice as proximate causes, it only underlines the ultimate cause all the more.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #13: Civilization always pursues complexity</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/civilization-always-pursues-complexity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2005 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/civilization-always-pursues-complexity/</guid>
      <description>What is &amp;ldquo;civilization&amp;rdquo;? When asked this question directly, many people answer that a civilization is simply a synonym for &amp;ldquo;society&amp;rdquo;&amp;ndash;that a civilization is simply a group of people living together. This definition is betrayed when you press the point with borderline examples. Are you comfortable with the phrase &amp;ldquo;Inuit Civilization&amp;rdquo;? Or &amp;ldquo;!Kung Civilization?&amp;rdquo; Or &amp;ldquo;Australian Aborigine Civilization&amp;rdquo;? Most people are not. There is no doubt as to whether the Inuit, !</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #12: Civilization must always grow</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/civilization-must-always-grow/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2005 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/civilization-must-always-grow/</guid>
      <description>Two suspects A, B are arrested by the police. The police have insufficient evidence for a conviction, and having separated both prisoners, visit each of them and offer the same deal: if one testifies for the prosecution (turns King&amp;rsquo;s Evidence) against the other and the other remains silent, the silent accomplice receives the full 10-year sentence and the betrayer goes free. If both stay silent, the police can only give both prisoners 6 months for a minor charge.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #11: Hierarchy is an unnecessary evil</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/hierarchy-is-an-unnecessary-evil/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2005 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/hierarchy-is-an-unnecessary-evil/</guid>
      <description>Egalitarianism is an essential part of human nature; it is the very thing that led to our humanity, and remains an undeniable yearning in the human spirit that continues to shape our political fortunes (*see* thesis #7. Hierarchy is the antithesis of that, and thus, we cannot avoid the inescapable conclusion that hierarchy itself is dehumanizing and maladapted to the human condition. It appears to suit many of our closest primate relatives just fine (chimpanzees, for example), but it denies the very thing that created us as a unique species&amp;ndash;our egalitarianism.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #10: Emergent elites led the Agricultural Revolution</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/emergent-elites-led-the-agricultural-revolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2005 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/emergent-elites-led-the-agricultural-revolution/</guid>
      <description>*How the Agricultural Revolution happened is well understood. It is perhaps best explained by David Rindos&amp;rsquo; Selectionist Hypothesis, which Jared Diamond explained succinctly in Guns, Germs and Steel* as a specific case of co-evolution. We could domesticate large herd mammals by identifying the leader; we could domesticate cereal grains because they were prone to harvesting. In the wild, a pea pod that doesn&amp;rsquo;t explode will simply die off, but to a human gatherer, such a pod filled with delicious peas is much more desirable than picking individual peas off the ground.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #9: Agriculture is difficult, dangerous and unhealthy</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/agriculture-is-difficult-dangerous-and-unhealthy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2005 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/agriculture-is-difficult-dangerous-and-unhealthy/</guid>
      <description>The previous thesis glossed over a number of significant points, which we must now go back and revisit in greater detail. The most glaring of these glosses is probably the assertion that agriculture is a risky, marginal and difficult means of acquiring food. Many readers would certainly object that agriculture provides a stable, secure and reliable source of food. After all, it was the bounty of agriculture that allowed us to give up hunting and gathering, constantly wandering and wondering where our next meal would come from, giving us the time to build civilization.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #8: Human societies are defined by their food</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/human-societies-are-defined-by-their-food/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Oct 2005 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/human-societies-are-defined-by-their-food/</guid>
      <description>Yehudi Cohen&amp;rsquo;s 1974 *Man in Adaptation* is the kind of classic that made its case so well, no one ever reads it. Most introductory anthropology textbooks will devote an entire chapter to Cohen&amp;rsquo;s framework&amp;ndash;a framework that modern anthropology simply takes for granted. Cohen divided the world&amp;rsquo;s cultures into any one of five &amp;ldquo;adaptive strategies&amp;rdquo;: foraging, horticulture, pastoralism, agriculture, and industrialism. Cohen noted the strong correlations these strategies had with the rest of their culture; so strong that, simply given a society&amp;rsquo;s mode of subsistence, accurate predictions could often be made about their level of political complexity, their kinship patterns, their population size and density, their modes of warfare, and even their religious beliefs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #7: Humans are best adapted to band life</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/humans-are-best-adapted-to-band-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2005 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/humans-are-best-adapted-to-band-life/</guid>
      <description>As we saw in the previous thesis, the division between our genus, Homo, and the Australopithecines occurred two million years ago, with *H. habilis* and his freakishly large brain. All primates have brain-to-body mass ratios that are much higher than normal, but the human ratio is remarkable even among primates. According to a study from the University of Liverpool, that disproportionately high brain-to-body mass ratio is determined by the size and complexity of their social groups.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #6: Humans are still Pleistocene animals</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/humans-are-still-pleistocene-animals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/humans-are-still-pleistocene-animals/</guid>
      <description>In 1833, Charles Lyell introduced the name “Holocene,” or “Recent Whole,” for our current geological epoch, stretching back only 10 or 12 thousand years. This makes the Holocene an incredibly young geological epoch, the shortest by far. The International Geological Congress in Bologna adopted the term in 1885, and it has been the accepted terminology ever since. The preceding geological epoch was the “last ice age,” the Pleistocene. It lasted for two million years, and while it was marked by significantly advanced glaciation, this was not the unremitting state of affairs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #5: Humans are neither good nor evil</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/humans-are-neither-good-nor-evil/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2005 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/humans-are-neither-good-nor-evil/</guid>
      <description>Are humans essentially good, or essentially evil? This is one of the most basic, perennial questions in philosophy. Many identify our individual answers to this question as determing our political spectrum–conservatives believe humans are inherently evil, and require strict rules to make them good, while liberals believe humans are inherently good, and must simply be free to act on such goodness. Both positions are unrealistic. Humans are products of evolution, and evolution is unconcerned with such abstractions as “good” or “evil.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #4: Human population is a function of food supply</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/human-population-is-a-function-of-food-supply/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2005 01:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/human-population-is-a-function-of-food-supply/</guid>
      <description>Thomas Malthus was one of the most influential thinkers of all time. His father knew Hume and Rousseau, and his own paper–*An Essay on the Principle of Population*–forever changed the way we think about populations and food supplies. It has informed food security policies worldwide, and provided the basic underpinnings of our modern concern with overpopulation. In The Origin of Species, Darwin called his theory of natural selection an application of the doctrines of Malthus in an area without the complicating factor of human intelligence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #3: Humans are products of evolution</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/humans-are-the-product-of-evolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2005 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/humans-are-the-product-of-evolution/</guid>
      <description>As we saw in the second thesis, natural selection is a tautology: anything that possesses some trait that makes it more likely to propogate itself, is more likely to propogate itself. Played out over a sufficiently long timeline, this can easily explain the origin of species. It was an explosive idea; not because it was theoretically lacking, nor even for lack of evidence. It was not even explosive for what it ruled out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #2: Evolution is the result of diversity</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/evolution-is-the-result-of-diversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2005 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/evolution-is-the-result-of-diversity/</guid>
      <description>The concept of progress is actually rather new. Most prehistoric and ancient peoples saw history as a constantly repeating cycle, incompatible with any notion of advancement or degradation. The first conceptions of linear time are found only in the historical era. Confuscius, the Greeks and the Jews all believed that the world was, in fact, becoming worse. In this, they did concieve of history as linear, but as the opposite of progress.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis #1: Diversity is the primary good</title>
      <link>http://rewild.com/anthropik/diversity-is-the-primary-good/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2005 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rewild.com/anthropik/diversity-is-the-primary-good/</guid>
      <description>Humans are social animals, and also capable of abstract, independent thought. The combination requires some form of social standards. Bees think with a single hive mind, and solitary animals do not encounter one another often enough to require a rigid system of morality and ethics. Without social norms, however, human society would break down. We have evolved in such societies, and require other humans to live. A single human, on his own, has little chance of survival.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>